Finding Aid for Episcopal Church, Diocese of Western Michigan records, 1851-2011
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Diocesan Committee Files
  - Standing Committee, Minutes, 1958-1969; 2 volumes (Box 63)
  - Finance Committee, Minutes, 1943-1969; 2 volumes (Box 63)
- Diocesan Organization Files
  The Diocesan Organization Files series includes the minutes from meetings of the Akeley Institute Board of Trustees, the Association of the Diocese of Western Michigan and its Board of Trustees, and the Semiannual Missionary Meeting. The records span 1875 to 1984.
  - Akeley Institute Board of Trustees, Minutes, 1911-1964 (Box 63)
  - Association of the Diocese of Western Michigan, Minutes, 1875-1984 (Box 63)
  - Association of the Diocese of Western Michigan Board of Trustees, Minutes, 1876-1985; 7 volumes (Box 64)
  - Semiannual Missionary Meeting, Minutes, 1875-1907 (Box 64)
- Diocesan Financial Records
  The Diocesan Financial Records series consists of four linear feet of volumes of the financial records covering a period from 1874 to 1952. The volumes document various funds managed by the diocese, as well as document the financial history of the diocese.
  - Bishop's Diocesan Emergency Fund, 1944-1949 (Box 65)
  - Cash Books, 1875-1930; 3 volumes (Box 65)
  - Episcopal Fund/ Episcopal Residency Fund, 1905-1909 (Box 65)
  - Executive Council Church Program Funds, 1922-1925; 4 volumes (Box 65)
  - Executive Council Church Program Funds, 1926-1934; 9 volumes (Box 66)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary Account, 1925-1928; 4 volumes (Box 67)
  - Interest Ledger, 1874-1923 (Box 67)
  - Investment Funds, 1875-1931; 2 volumes (Box 68)
  - Missionary Treasurer's Ledger, 1950-1952 (Box 68)
  - Receivables and Mortgages, 1875-1921 (Box 68)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series contains photographs of personalities and buildings associated with the diocese, as well as photographs of parish and mission churches. There are also slides and videotapes of church consecration services and of the Cathedral of Christ the King.
  - Photographs
    - Personalities, Buildings etc.
      - Akeley Hall (Volume 15)
      - Bishop Bennison (Box 69)
      - Bishop Bennison, Visit to Kimberley and Kuruman, 1962 (Box 69)
      - Bishop McNeil (Box 69)
      - Bishop Whittemore (Box 69)
      - Bonnell House Conference Center (Box 69)
      - Clergy and Ceremonies, circa 1977-1985 (Box 69)
      - Conventions and Conferences (Box 69)
        (see also oversize folder UBAl)
      - Diocesan Convention, 1967; 1980 (Box 69)
      - Diocesan Offices (Box 69)
      - Diocesan Officers (Box 69)
      - Diocesan Clergy Conventions, 1954; 1967-1976 (Folder UBAm)
    - Parish and Mission Churches
      - Ada-Cascade (Box 69)
      - Albion (Box 69)
      - Allegan (Box 69)
      - Battle Creek (Box 69)
      - Beaver Island (Box 69)
      - Benton Harbor (Box 69)
      - Benzonia (Box 69)
      - Big Rapids (Box 69)
      - Cadillac (Box 69)
      - Coldwater (Box 69)
      - Conway (Box 69)
      - Dowagiac (Box 69)
      - Elk Rapids (Box 69)
      - Fremont (Box 69)
      - Grand Haven (Box 69)
      - Grand Junction (Box 69)
      - Grand Ledge (Box 69)
      - Grand Rapids
        - Grace Church (Box 69)
        - St. Andrew's (Box 69)
        - St. Mark's (Box 69)
        - St. Paul's (Box 69)
        - St. Philip's (Box 69)
      - Greenville (Box 69)
      - Gull Lake (Box 69)
      - Harbor Springs (Box 69)
      - Hastings (Box 69)
      - Holland (Box 69)
    - Parish and Mission Churches (cont.)
      - Ionia (Box 69)
      - Kalamazoo
        - Kanley Memorial Chapel (Box 69)
        - St. Aidan's (Box 69)
        - St. Luke's (Box 69)
        - St. Martin's (Box 69)
      - Kentwood (Box 69)
      - Lakeside (Box 69)
      - Lansing (Box 69)
      - Ludington (Box 69)
      - Manistee (Box 69)
      - Montague-Whitehall (Box 69)
      - Mt. Pleasant (Box 69)
      - Muskegon
        - St. Alban's (Box 69)
        - St. Gregory's (Box 69)
        - St. Paul's (Box 69)
      - Newaygo (Box 69)
      - Niles (Box 69)
      - Omena (Box 69)
      - Onekema (Box 69)
      - Orangeville (Box 69)
      - Paw Paw (Box 69)
      - Pentwater (Box 69)
      - Petoskey (Box 69)
      - Plainwell (Box 69)
      - Portage (Box 69)
      - Richland (Box 69)
      - St. Joseph (Box 69)
      - Saugatuck (Box 69)
      - South Haven (Box 69)
      - Sparta (Box 69)
      - Starr Commonwealth (Box 69)
      - Sturgis (Box 69)
      - Three Rivers
        - St. Gregory's Priory (Box 69)
        - Trinity (Box 69)
      - Traverse City (Box 69)
      - Wyoming (Box 69)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 69)
      - Photograph Scrapbook, 1941-1948 (Box 69)
    - Miscellaneous (largely unprocessed)
      - Church Cathedral (Box 108)
      - Portraits of Bishops and with others (Box 108)
      - Bishop Bennison (Box 108)
      - Bishop Lee (Box 108)
    - Slides (largely unidentified) (Box 108)
  - Videotapes, VHS
    - The Cathedral of Christ the King, undated; 16:28 (Box 109)
    - The Consecration of Edward Lewis Lee, Jr., undated (Box 109)
    - A Conversation with Bishop Lee, January 1996 (Box 109)
    - The Liturgy for the Ordination and Consecration of Robert R. Gepert as a Bishop in the Church of God and Bishop Coadjutor of the Diocese of Western Michigan, April 27, 2002 (Box 109)
- Sound recordings, 17 audiocassettes
  The Sound Recordings series includes cassette tapes of meetings of the annual convention.
  - Recordings of annual conventions of the diocese, 1995; 1998; 2004 (Box 109)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series contains newspaper clippings and other materials relating to the activities of the diocese. The scrapbooks date from 1911 to 1987.
  - Diocesan Scrapbook, 1911-1950; 3 volumes (Box 70)
  - Diocesan Scrapbook, 1950-1959 (Volume 16)
  - Diocesan Scrapbook, 1960-1969 (Box 70)
  - Bishop Whittemore Foundation Scrapbook, 1952 (Box 70)
  - Annual Convention Scrapbook, 1964 (Box 70)
  - Diocesan Scrapbooks, 1969-1987; 2 volumes
    - Diocesan Scrapbooks, 1969-1987 (Volume 17)
    - Diocesan Scrapbooks, 1969-1987 (Volume 18)
- Western Michigan University (WMU) Ministry Files (1949-1992)
  The Western Michigan University (WMU) Ministry Files contains files arranged alphabetically, which cover the time period 1949-1992. The papers relate to the activities and outreach of the diocese to the community of WMU.
  - Bronco Bash, 1988-1991 (Box 71)
  - "Called to Teach" Conference, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
  - Campus Council Correspondence, 1987-1990 (Box 71)
  - Canterbury Center, Campus Ministry Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 71)
  - Canterbury Club Historical File, 1949-1978 (Box 71)
  - Chaplain Job Descriptions, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
  - Chaplains at WMU, 1986-1988 (Box 71)
  - Commission on Growth and Development, 1987-1988 (Box 71)
  - Creighton, Susan (Chaplain), 1987-1989 (Box 71)
  - The Croft Retreat and Study Center, 1987-1989 (Box 71)
  - Cursillo Weekends, undated (Box 71)
  - Diocesan Campus Work, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
  - Diocese of Western Michigan Bishop's Advisory Committee on Campus Ministry, 1985-1987; 1991; 2 folders (Box 71)
  - Diocese of Western Michigan Convention, 1991 (Box 71)
  - Diocese of Western Michigan Executive Council, 1990-1991 (Box 71)
  - Episcopal Church Women, 1987-1990 (Box 71)
  - Episcopal/ Lutheran Cooperation at WMU, 1986-1989 (Box 71)
  - Episcopal Society for Ministry in Higher Education (ESMHE), 1990 (Box 71)
  - Episcopal Youth Council, 1987-1991 (Box 71)
  - Evaluation of Campus Ministry, 1989 (Box 71)
  - Faculty Contacts, circa 1980s (Box 71)
  - Friends of St. Aidan's, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
  - Harvest Evangelical Free Church, 1991 (Box 71)
  - "Issues and Choices in Campus Ministry Evaluation" by A.J. Burry, 1985 (Box 71)
  - Kenyon College Conference, 1989 (Box 71)
  - Medieval Studies, 1988-1990 (Box 71)
  - Pastoral Care, 1988 (Box 71)
  - "Prayer in a Hectic World" Series, 1988 (Box 71)
  - Presiding Bishop's Consultation on Mission in Higher Education, 1989 (Box 71)
  - Province V Campus Ministry, 1988-1991 (Box 71)
  - St. Aidan's
    - Building Requirements, 1964 (Box 71)
    - Calendar, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
    - Campus Ministry Proposed Organizational Structure, 1987-1989 (Box 71)
    - Chapel Budgets, 1986-1987 (Box 71)
    - Chapel Building Usage, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
    - Finances, 1987-1991 (Box 71)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1986-1992 (Box 71)
    - Programming, 1986-1990 (Box 71)
    - Register of church services, 1966-1992; 2 volumes in 1 folder (Box 71)
    - Secretary, 1987-1988 (Box 71)
    - Sexton, 1991 (Box 71)
    - Student Cards, 1990 (Box 71)
    - Worship, 1986-1988 (Box 71)
  - "Spiritual Journey" Series, 1989-1990 (Box 71)
  - Student Lists, 1988-1989 (Box 71)
  - Task Force on Christian Education, 1990 (Box 71)
  - Thanksgiving Dinner, 1987-1988 (Box 71)
  - Western Herald (newspaper), 1988 (Box 71)
  - Western Michigan University Business Office, 1987-1989 (Box 71)
  - "Women and Spirituality" Series, 1988 (Box 71)
  - Youth and Education Representatives, 1990 (Box 71)
- Women's Organization Files
  The Women's Organization Files series consists of one linear foot of records from the Episcopal Churchwomen which cover the period from 1952 to 1997. Papers of note in this series are Annual Meeting Reports, minutes from the Executive Committee, and Treasurer's Reports.
  - Women's Auxiliary, Minutes, 1900-1941; 2 volumes (Box 72)
  - Women's Auxiliary to the Board of Missions
    - Minutes, 1881-1925; 2 volumes (Box 72)
    - Secretary's Record Book, 1906-1908; 2 volumes (Box 72)
    - Yearbooks, 1950-1958 (Box 72)
    - Annual Reports, 1905-1928 (Box 72)
  - Women of the Church
    - Minutes, 1944-1955 (Box 72)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1941-1963 (Box 72)
    - Yearbooks, 1941-1950 (Box 72)
  - Episcopal Churchwomen, Handbook, 1965 (Box 72)
  - Episcopal Churchwomen (Box 73)
    - Annual Meeting Reports, 1957-1997; 7 folders (Box 73)
    - Executive Board Minutes, 1952-1992; 7 folders (Box 73)
    - Newsletters, 1981-1991 (Box 73)
    - Treasurer's Reports, 1961-1987; 6 folders (Box 73)
- Miscellaneous office and staff files
  The Miscellaneous office and staff files series contains a miscellanea of files of different church officials and church committees. These include the Diocesan Deployment Office, files relating to the Cathedral Church, and miscellaneous financial materials. Included in this series are files relating to the Cathedral building: planning and fund raising material, the art within the building, publicity, programs of various dedicatory services, and related information.
  - Dean of the Cathedral Church (Benjamin Lavey and others) files (Box 98)
  - Ruth Meyers (Asst. Professor of Liturgies, Diocesan Liturgies, Diocese of Western Michigan) files (Box 99)
    (include liturgical guidelines)
  - Companion Diocese Coordinator (Donald G. May) (Box 99)
    (regarding diocese in Nigeria)
  - Reports of the Missionary Treasurer of the Diocese of Western Michigan, 1949-1963 (Box 99)
  - Reports of the Treasurer of the Annual Convention, 1939-1963 (Box 100)
  - Financial Statements and Auditor's reports, 1931; 1961-1994 (scattered) (Box 100)
  - Reports of the Treasurer of the Executive Council, 1929-1932; 1944-1945 (Box 100)
  - Financial Statements of the Bishop Whittemore Foundation (Box 100)
  - Endowment Giving for Parishes of the Episcopal Church, Diocese of Western Michigan, 1998 (Box 100)
  - Association of the Diocese of West Michigan, Consolidated Account, June 8, 1995 (Box 100)
  - Association of the Diocese of West Michigan various financial statements and accounts, 1937-1939 (Box 100)
  - Cathedral Corporation audits, 1969-1978 (Box 100)
  - Diocesan Deployment Office
    - Battle Creek. Resurrection, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Benton Harbor-Harbert. St. Augustine's, 4 folders (Box 101)
    - Beulah. St. Philip's, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Cadillac. St. Mark's (Box 101)
    - Cascade. St. Michael's (Box 101)
    - Fremont. St. John (Box 101)
    - Grand Ledge. Trinity (Box 101)
    - Grand Rapids. Grace (Box 101)
    - Grand Rapids. St. Philip's, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Muskegon. St. Alban's, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Newaygo. St. Mark's (Box 101)
    - Niles. Trinity (Box 101)
    - Plainwell. St. Stephen's, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Portage. St. Barnabas, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Sparta. St. Matthew's, 2 folders (Box 101)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 101)
  - Assessment Review Committee
    - General (Box 102)
    - Montague, St. Peter's (Box 102)
    - Mt. Pleasant, St. John's (Box 102)
    - Portage, St. Barnabas (Box 102)
  - Treasurer (L.J. Wetherbee file), 1962-1964 (Box 102)
  - Miscellaneous Office Files
    - Alcohol and drug abuse, 1985-1986 (Box 102)
    - Association of the Diocese of Western Michigan, 1961-1972 (Box 102)
    - Capital Fund Drive, 1985-1986 (Box 102)
    - Chancellors and Bishops meetings, 1982-1988; 1991-1992 (Box 102)
    - Church Pension Fund, 1969-1988 (Box 102)
    - Clergy Association, 1973-1977; 1982-1984 (Box 102)
    - Committee on Community Life and Participation, 1969-1970 (Box 102)
    - Committee on Finance
      - 1965-1971 (Box 102)
      - 1980-1981 (Box 102)
    - Correspondence (miscellaneous), 1979-1988 (Box 102)
    - Diocesan Center / Diocesan Land Site, Portage, 1965-1977 (Box 102)
    - Jubilee Ministry, 1997 (Box 102)
    - Lee, Edward L. (sermons published in diocesan newsletters), 1989-1992 (Box 102)
    - Marriage Canons, 1946-1948 (Box 102)
    - Membership materials marriages, baptisms, burials, transfers, 1970s (Box 102)
    - Organization -- Preliminary Study Committee on the Organization of the Church in the Diocese, 1975-1984 (Box 102)
    - Rural Deans, 1983-1988 (Box 102)
    - Service Cross Recipients (to 1980s) (Box 102)
    - Stewardship letters, 1982 (Box 102)
  - Bishop's search committee, 1984 (Box 112)
  - Diocesan Consulting Team, 1991 (Box 112)
  - Search Committee / Transition Committee, 2000 (Box 112)
  - Planning / Programs
    - Year of Identity, 1991 (Box 113)
    - Days of Vision, 1992 (Box 113)
    - Year of Action, 1993 (Box 113)
    - Year of the Small Church Task Force, 1997 (Box 113)
    - Planning for Tomorrow Conferences, 2000; 2004 (Box 113)
  - St. Aidan's Campus Ministry (Box 113)
  - Anniversary Celebrations
    - Centennial, 1971-1974 (Box 113)
    - 125th Anniversary, 1999 (Box 113)
  - Cathedral Building: Fund-raising, Construction, Carillon, etc.
    - Art in the Cathedral (Box 114)
    - Bell Carillon
      - General, 1968-1969 (Box 114)
      - Contract, specifications, and photographs (Box 114)
      - Gifts (Box 114)
        (also include some later dated material)
    - Proposed sale of carillon, 2007 (Box 114)
    - Building fund, gifts, and memorials (Box 114)
    - Canon and Charter, 1942; 1965-1967 (Box 114)
    - Cathedral Campaign, Diocesan Center, 1965-1966 (Box 114)
    - Cathedral Campaign, Fund Raising, 1964-1969 (Box 114)
    - Cathedral Congregation, 1967-1969 (Box 114)
    - Cathedral Congregation Advisory Committee, 1967-1969 (Box 114)
    - Cathedral Consecration, 1977 (Box 114)
    - Cathedral Corporation, 1966-1968 (Box 114)
    - Correspondence, General, 1966-1969 (Box 114)
    - Diocesan Center, undated (Box 114)
    - Diocesan Center Campaign, 1965-1966; 2 folders (Box 114)
    - Enthronement, Bishop Charles E. Bennison, 1969 (Box 114)
    - Ground Breaking Ceremony, 1967 (Box 114)
    - Kneelers for Cathedral, 1969-1971 (Box 114)
    - Memorial Fund, 1968 (Box 114)
    - Michigan Annual Report, 1968 (Box 114)
    - Opening Service, 1969 (Box 114)
    - Organ, 1965-1967 (Box 114)
    - Programs: cornerstone 1968 dedication, 1969 (Box 114)
    - Publicity, 1966-1969; 1987 (Box 114)
    - Service Schedule, 1969 (Box 114)
    - Tremble, Sidney B., 1965-1966 (Box 114)
- Bulletins of church services -- Cathedral Church of Christ the King
  The Bulletins are the weekly order of service for the Cathedral Church of Christ the King. The bulletins date from 1968 to 2003.
  - 1968-1981, 23 folders (Box 115)
  - 1982-1991, 20 folders (Box 116)
  - 1992-September 2003, 35 folders (Box 117)
- Church of Christ the King
  The following series comprise most of the 2012 accession: Church of Christ the King, Miscellaneous parish materials, and Miscellaneous diocesan materials.
  The Church of Christ the King series consists of administrative and financial documents, vestry and other meeting minutes, parish newsletters (Chimes), photographs (slides), and scrapbooks, as well as other assorted materials including selected sermons by Rev. Cynthia L. Black. Related materials May be found under Miscellaneous office and staff files, Cathedral building and under Visual Materials, Photographs, Cathedral.
  - Administrative documents
    - By-laws, 1991-2000 (Box 118)
    - Correspondence and financial information, 1990 (Box 118)
    - Statues for the Cathedral Corporation and for the Cathedral Church, 1967 (Box 118)
  - Annual meetings, 1989-1992 (Box 118)
  - Annual report, 1997; 1998 (Box 118)
  - Cathedral Chapter meeting materials, 1992 (Box 118)
  - CBGC meeting minutes, 1990 (Box 118)
  - Events
    - AIDS Exhibit, October 1993 (Box 118)
    - Confirmation service materials and records, 1994-2003 (Box 118)
  - Financial documents
    - Application for financial assistance to the diocese, 1992 (Box 118)
    - Miscellaneous, 1989-1997; 2 folders (Box 118)
  - Minutes of Vestry and Council meetings, 1989-2005; 4 folders (Box 118)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Cathedral floor plan (Box 118)
    - Heraldry seal/Coat-of-Arms (Box 118)
    - Inventory, 1992 (Box 118)
    - Mixed materials, 1990-1997 (Box 118)
    - Search committee materials (for a new rector), circa 1990 (Box 118)
    - Stewardship materials, circa 1990 (Box 118)
    - Vestry documents, 1993-1995 (Box 118)
    - Vestry and delegate documents, 1996-2005; 2 folders (Box 118)
    - Vestry membership lists, 1997-2005 (Box 118)
  - Newsletters, 1990-2006; 6 folders (Box 118)
  - Sermons, 1991-1992 (Box 118)
  - Photographic slide sets (Box 119)
    - Slide carousel of the Cathedral from the land purchase in 1967 to the completion of the building in 1969 with additional loose slides dating from 1970-1981 of the building, events, and people, 1967-1981 (Box 119)
    - Slide carousel with "Eighty Views of the Cathedral Church of Christ the King" (descriptions enclosed), 1971 (Box 119)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Scrapbook compiled by John and Laura van Dyke of newspaper clippings, ephemera, and photographs related to the construction of the cathedral, 1967-1970 (Box 119)
    - Scrapbooks of correspondence, blueprints, news clippings, and photographs related to Mr. and Mrs. William P. Favorite's donation of bas-relief sculptures to the cathedral, 1968-1969; 2 volumes (Box 119)
    - Scrapbook of newspaper clippings and photographs related to the construction of the cathedral, 1965-1969 (Volume 19)
- Miscellaneous parish materials
  The Miscellaneous parish materials series contains materials collected from various parishes within the diocese. The materials are arranged by city alphabetically and then by parish name and include photographs as well as programs and other documents.
  - Grand Rapids
    - Grace Episcopal Church mailings, 2005 (Box 120)
    - St. Michael's Episcopal Church art auction photographs, 2004 (Box 120)
    - St. Philip's Episcopal Church centennial program, 2011 (Box 120)
  - Greenville
    - St. Paul's visitation photographs, 2004 (Box 120)
  - Saint Joseph
    - St. Paul's Episcopal Parish youth pilgrimage fundraising letter, 2004 (Box 120)
- Miscellaneous diocesan materials
  The Miscellaneous diocesan materials series consists of materials related to the diocese as a whole. This includes materials related to events such as the orientation for new clergy as well as items of correspondence sent to many or all parishes in the diocese. Related materials May be found in the Miscellaneous office and staff files series.
  - Access to the ordination process (for those in homosexual relationships) correspondence and statements, 1992-1998 (Box 120)
  - Applications for sabbatical leave grants, 2000-2001 (Box 120)
  - Constitution and canons, 1987 (Box 120)
  - Correspondence (over fax) with parishes, 2001-2002 (Box 120)
  - Events
    - Bishop and diocesan staff meetings, 2005 (Box 120)
    - Collected materials on conference/retreat centers (Box 120)
    - First spiritual discernment group photographs, undated (Box 120)
    - NNECA [National Network of Episcopal Clergy Associations] XXVI [conference], 1996 (Box 120)
    - New Clergy Orientation, 2001 (Box 120)
    - Retired Clergy Luncheon, 2000 (Box 120)
    - Unlabeled negatives from group gathering, circa 2005 (Box 120)
  - Guidelines for the Celebration of the Rites of Christian Initiation and Renewal of Faith, 1994 (Box 120)
  - Mixed correspondence and other materials, 1983; 2005 (Box 120)
  - Order of the Daughters of the King eNews, 2005 (Box 120)
  - Pondera Advisors (leadership consulting) (Box 120)
  - Reports
    - The Bishop Whittemore Foundation report of examination, 1962 (Box 120)
    - The Diaconal Formation Process report, 1990 (Box 120)